<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>watches on Hayaan&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>https://omega1510.github.io/blog/tags/watches/</link>
    <description>Recent content in watches on Hayaan&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 28 Aug 2023 20:33:07 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://omega1510.github.io/blog/tags/watches/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Watches Aren&#39;t Investments</title>
      <link>https://omega1510.github.io/blog/posts/0007/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Aug 2023 20:33:07 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://omega1510.github.io/blog/posts/0007/</guid>
      <description>They are emotional purchases, not rational ones.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>As the owner of a <em>very</em> small and cheap watch collection, I am in no way qualified to comment on the practice of buying luxury watches as investment opportunities. My most expensive watch does not even crack four figures, and none of the pieces in my collection are likely to provide me a return-on-investment.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup> Still—whether out of spite or because I have no stake in the result, I don&rsquo;t know—I am going to write out my opinion on the matter.</p>
<p>An argument can be made that watches are great investments. <a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2023-02-16/luxury-swiss-watches-still-beat-stocks-and-crypto-despite-rolex-and-patek-drop">According to Bloomberg</a>, luxury Swiss watches have consistently beat stocks and crypto over the past few years. I am bombarded with videos of millionaire watch salesmen preaching the benefits of buying a $50,000 Patek Phillipe.</p>
<p>However, this betrays the real reason people should be buying watches. Many decades ago, watches were tools; now, they are jewelry. Nonetheless, like all tools or jewelry, watches are meant to be <em>worn</em>, not locked up in a safety deposit box. Yes, every dent on the case and scratch on the crystal drains value, but it adds character.</p>
<p>And watches aren&rsquo;t meant to be investments, either. If someone had cash to burn and wanted to grow it, they would invest in something much more lucrative. We buy watches because we <em>like</em> them; it is a deeply emotional purchase. I think we are too fed up with how it holds value or how it looks on our wrist, not about how much we like it. To reduce something so beautiful, with such intricate engineering, to just an investment is a disservice to the world of horology.</p>
<section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
<p>Unless, of course, the current Russo-Ukrainian War sends the price of my Russian or Soviet pieces skyrocketing. <em>Obi-<strong>War</strong> Kenobi, you&rsquo;re my only hope&hellip;</em>&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
