<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>personal on Hayaan&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>https://hayaan.me/tags/personal/</link>
    <description>Recent content in personal on Hayaan&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 05 Sep 2023 16:25:39 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://hayaan.me/tags/personal/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>I Can&#39;t Do What I Love</title>
      <link>https://hayaan.me/posts/0014/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Sep 2023 16:25:39 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hayaan.me/posts/0014/</guid>
      <description>A rant about making money following my passion.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I am starting to apply to colleges, and beginning that process involves first choosing what major to study. I love biology and chemistry, so I am naturally inclined to choose biochemistry. However, there are a number of issues that prevent me from pursuing what I would love to do in the future.</p>
<p>First, if I am to major in biochemistry, I am more-or-less forced to pursue a doctoral degree. To quit my education with just a Bachelor&rsquo;s would be to condemn myself to a poor job outlook. Most companies in biotech are looking for candidates with a Ph.D. or M.D., and jobs for recent graduates with just a Bachelor&rsquo;s are few and far between, often with disappointing salaries.</p>
<p>Second, I do not want to be a physician, and there aren&rsquo;t many options for lucrative careers in biology that do not involve practicing medicine. I would love to research and teach, not work with patients. The classic path for doing research is a Ph.D., but putting in nearly a decade of work to make less than what a doctor does doesn&rsquo;t sound appealing to me.</p>
<p>The only upside to doing a Ph.D. that I can see is the lower cost. People regularly leave medical school with half a million dollars in student debt. In contrast, doctoral students usually get a stipend from the lab they work at which mostly covers the cost of the program, and they can teach a little bit to make up the difference in cash.</p>
<p>I would love to do a Ph.D. and have great job prospects afterwards that are not limited to academia. It would be great to do research in a lab somewhere and live a life where I am doing what I love. Unfortunatly, in the current education landscape, that does not seem to be possible. For now, I plan to apply as a biochemistry major and complete my undergraduate degree. Then I will see what the future holds.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cities Upon a Hill</title>
      <link>https://hayaan.me/posts/0012/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Sep 2023 18:32:10 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hayaan.me/posts/0012/</guid>
      <description>Social media is dying.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I don&rsquo;t have any social media. I never have. But every day I am swarmed with signals from the top platforms on the web to JOIN JOIN JOIN! And when the signals aren&rsquo;t directly from them, they are from friends and family, who subtly give me funny looks when I tell them that I don&rsquo;t have an Instagram.</p>
<p>Yesterday, I nearly made a Mastodon account. <em>Nearly.</em> While Mastodon is great as far as social media platforms go, it is still fundamentaly a breed of app I don&rsquo;t want anything to do with.</p>
<p>Manuel Moreale <a href="https://manuelmoreale.com/places-on-the-web">wrote</a> yesterday:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Big social media platforms are the metropolis: dense, busy, chaotic. They’re the place that never sleeps and there’s always something new going on.<br>
&hellip;<br>
There was a time when forums were the cities of the web but now are more like small towns. They’re the place where people congregate around shared interests.<br>
&hellip;<br>
And then there’re personal sites, the house in the forest. It’s the place people escape to when they’re tired of the noise.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Big social media platforms have gone from cities upon a hill to something that resembles today&rsquo;s San Francisco: dirty, crime-ridden, and dying. I think I&rsquo;ll stick to my house in the forest, even if nobody is here with me.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>School Has Started</title>
      <link>https://hayaan.me/posts/0010/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Sep 2023 20:16:17 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hayaan.me/posts/0010/</guid>
      <description>The beginning of the end.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>My senior year of high school started on Monday. I am expecting a brutal few months, filled with countlessly revising long college essays in the hopes of gaining admission somewhere I won&rsquo;t totally hate.</p>
<p>It is not all bad, though. I really only have three difficult classes: Honors English, AP Psychology, and AP Macroeconomics. I may decide to self-study AP Literature, but I don&rsquo;t know yet.</p>
<p>The school is also giving us Tuesdays and Thursdays off, and Fridays are half-days, so every week is more-or-less an easy week. And there is a big international trip in December I am looking forward to.</p>
<p>As to how this development relates to the blog, I&rsquo;m not sure. I may not write as much if I am overburdened with work during the school year. Or, I may write a lot now that I have another source of stimuli and reflection in my life. Who knows?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On Sleep</title>
      <link>https://hayaan.me/posts/0009/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Sep 2023 19:31:12 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hayaan.me/posts/0009/</guid>
      <description>I really need more of it...</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>It is He who made the night a garment for you, and sleep a rest, and made the day like a resurrection. (Quran 25:47)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>School has started up again this week. On the second day of English class, the teacher showed <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=5MuIMqhT8DM">this Ted Talk</a> about sleep to us. The video discussed the numerous consequenses of not getting a good night&rsquo;s sleep. The ones that stood out most to me were:</p>
<ul>
<li>Lowered intelligence by 40%</li>
<li>Inability to commit events to long-term memory</li>
<li>Increase in rates of car accidents and heart attacks</li>
<li>Promotion of cancer and harm to the immune system</li>
</ul>
<p>I really need to start focusing on my sleep. My nighttime routine involves washing up, praying, and reading a book before slowly drifting to sleep. Some nights, I don&rsquo;t fall asleep until 1am. I will just lie there with my eyes open for an hour and half, blink, and wake up five hours later.</p>
<p>The most simple improvement is just going to bed earlier. Reading action-packed novels can keep my mind awake long after I put the book down, so avoiding these types of books when I am winding down is also key.</p>
<p>Here is the video. I encourage everyone to watch it.</p>

<div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
  <iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/5MuIMqhT8DM" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video"></iframe>
</div>

]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
