<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>meta on Hayaan&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>https://hayaan.me/tags/meta/</link>
    <description>Recent content in meta on Hayaan&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 09:59:49 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://hayaan.me/tags/meta/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>One Month</title>
      <link>https://hayaan.me/posts/0031/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 09:59:49 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hayaan.me/posts/0031/</guid>
      <description>A small milestone.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This blog&rsquo;s <a href="posts/0001/">first post</a> was on August 20. Today&rsquo;s date is September 20. That marks one month that this blog has been active. Yay!</p>
<p>I still don&rsquo;t feel any real effects from the blog. Maybe that will take a little bit longer. I do, however, look forward to posting every day, so that&rsquo;s good.</p>
<p>The next milestone will probably be at 6 months.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Setting Up a Custom Domain</title>
      <link>https://hayaan.me/posts/0022/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Sep 2023 19:23:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hayaan.me/posts/0022/</guid>
      <description>It&amp;#39;s important for the longevity of the web.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Using a custom domain on your website is great for all the obvious reasons. It forms a brand identity, keeps your site memorable, and looks much better than <code>username.github.io</code>, for example.</p>
<p>But, it&rsquo;s important for another reason: longevity. No web server is forever. Your website <strong>will</strong> die some day in the future in an irrecoverable way. When that happens, you will be forced to transfer it to a new server. If you don&rsquo;t own your domain, all the links to your content that you have accumulated throughout the years will die with your old server. With a custom domain, maintaining hyperlinks in the event of a catastrophic faliure is as simple as editing a couple lines of text.</p>
<p>It is for this reason that I have finally purchased a custom domain for this blog: <a href="https://hayaan.me/">https://hayaan.me/</a>. I hope you will too for your site.</p>
<p>P.S. Domain records are <em>way</em> more complicated and slow than they ought to be.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Opting Out of AI Web Scraping</title>
      <link>https://hayaan.me/posts/0011/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Sep 2023 22:02:56 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hayaan.me/posts/0011/</guid>
      <description>Why do I have to &amp;#34;opt-out?&amp;#34;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>If you open my website&rsquo;s <a href="https://omega1510.github.io/robots.txt">robots.txt</a>, you will see that it includes the following lines:</p>
<div class="highlight"><div class="chroma">
<table class="lntable"><tr><td class="lntd">
<pre tabindex="0" class="chroma"><code><span class="lnt">1
</span><span class="lnt">2
</span><span class="lnt">3
</span><span class="lnt">4
</span><span class="lnt">5
</span></code></pre></td>
<td class="lntd">
<pre tabindex="0" class="chroma"><code class="language-yaml" data-lang="yaml"><span class="nt">User-agent</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="l">GPTBot</span><span class="w">
</span><span class="w"></span><span class="nt">Disallow</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="l">/</span><span class="w">
</span><span class="w">
</span><span class="w"></span><span class="nt">User-agent</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="l">ChatGPT-User</span><span class="w">
</span><span class="w"></span><span class="nt">Disallow</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="l">/</span><span class="w">
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table>
</div>
</div><p>What do these lines of code do? Well, they stop OpenAI&rsquo;s ChatGPT from learning from my blog.</p>
<p>OpenAI recently unveiled GPTBot, a piece of software that lets them harvest data from the web to train their artificial intelligence models on. If you take issue with that, like I do, then adding those lines to your website prevent it from scraping the content you wrote.</p>
<p>I, and many other people, don&rsquo;t want artifical intelligence benefiting from my blood, sweat, and tears for free. I find it deplorable that you must &ldquo;opt-out&rdquo; of this process. What about people who have no idea that their data is being harvested and used, or who aren&rsquo;t technically inclined enough to block GPTBot? Will their data be used without compensation until the end of time?</p>
<p>The way it should work is that you must opt-in specifically, and only then will OpenAI scrape your website. Unfortunately, we all know this won&rsquo;t happen. All OpenAI cares about is profit, and that won&rsquo;t happen if they actually respect people&rsquo;s basic right to privacy.</p>
<p>I recently talked about this with a friend. He told me that AI is the future of using the web, and if I block ChatGPT, I&rsquo;m going to lose out on a lot of readers. My opinion may change in the future, but as of now, so be it.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hello, world!</title>
      <link>https://hayaan.me/posts/0001/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Aug 2023 18:44:27 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hayaan.me/posts/0001/</guid>
      <description>Why I write.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2 id="motivation">Motivation</h2>
<p>I think it&rsquo;s fitting for the first post on this blog to be an explanation of why I&rsquo;m writing.</p>
<p>One of my friends recently began posting more of his thoughts on social media because he felt that writing had taken a backseat in his life. He wanted to rekindle that quickly fading love for the pen. I don&rsquo;t think that&rsquo;s the case with me.</p>
<p>Neither do I want to attract followers or make money. If I wanted to do that, I would be posting AI-generated content somewhere with more eyes, like Medium.</p>
<p>I discovered a quote that I think sums up my thoughts nicely. Amit G. <a href="https://amitg.blog/my-daughter-was-writing-in-her-journal-today-and-casually-asked-me-why-she-does">writes</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>My daughter went on to scribble happily in her journal. Once she was done, she said, “I love how I feel when I capture everything on my mind in these pages.”</p>
<p>Even I want that now.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I want to write because there is something trapped inside of me angry that I won&rsquo;t let it out. There are way to many thoughts in my head, fighting to be put down on paper. I want this blog to be a place where I can let the little <a href="https://allpoetry.com/poem/8509539-Bluebird-by-Charles-Bukowski">bluebird</a> in my soul roam free, at least for a little while.</p>
<h2 id="future-plans">Future Plans</h2>
<p>This blog will have absolutely no AI-generated content. It will have no advertisements, tracking, or harvesting of data. It will be raw and free: a place where I can write down my thoughts for the world to see.</p>
<p>I recently came across <a href="https://juliacameronlive.com/basic-tools/morning-pages/">Julia Cameron&rsquo;s Morning Pages</a>, where you write three pages from the heart stream-of-conciousness style every morning. That&rsquo;s a little too hardcore for me.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m aiming for posting about 300 words every day on this blog. Some days I&rsquo;ll write more, some days less. It&rsquo;s all about building a habit. Let&rsquo;s see how it goes.</p>
<p><strong>Update:</strong> I have enabled completely anonymized tracking. Nothing personally identifiable, even your IP address, is collected.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
