<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>technology on Hayaan&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>https://hayaan.me/tags/technology/</link>
    <description>Recent content in technology on Hayaan&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 14 Sep 2023 21:46:03 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://hayaan.me/tags/technology/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Privacy with the Google Nest Hub</title>
      <link>https://hayaan.me/posts/0023/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Sep 2023 21:46:03 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hayaan.me/posts/0023/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;#39;m on the fence about keeping it.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I have slowly been removing more and more Google products from my life over concerns about their privacy, or lack thereof. I switched to DuckDuckGo, left Chrome for Firefox, and so on. So, like the inconsistent wreck I am, I have gotten my hands on a Google Nest Hub that I promptly set up on my bedside table.</p>
<p>Like any Google product, its filled with blatant grabs for my data in the name of improving the company&rsquo;s products and services. I have said no to everything I can, but still I&rsquo;m uneasy about keeping it. It&rsquo;s a substantial upgrade over my previous alarm clock, given that it can set multiple alarms (the main feature I need) and also has all the Google Assistant stuff. However, there is something that erks me about keeping a motion sensor and microphone pointed at me all night, especially when all that data is going straight to Google&rsquo;s servers.</p>
<p>I would feel much better about this if the data stayed on my device. But Google sends so many data points to their servers that really doesn&rsquo;t need to be there. One can&rsquo;t even ask Google Assistant for the time without being connected to the internet.</p>
<p>In the end, I&rsquo;m on the fence about keeping it. Don&rsquo;t get me wrong, it&rsquo;s an amazing product, but I am bothered by having a smart display run by Google, of all companies.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Setting Up a Custom Domain</title>
      <link>https://hayaan.me/posts/0022/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Sep 2023 19:23:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hayaan.me/posts/0022/</guid>
      <description>It&amp;#39;s important for the longevity of the web.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Using a custom domain on your website is great for all the obvious reasons. It forms a brand identity, keeps your site memorable, and looks much better than <code>username.github.io</code>, for example.</p>
<p>But, it&rsquo;s important for another reason: longevity. No web server is forever. Your website <strong>will</strong> die some day in the future in an irrecoverable way. When that happens, you will be forced to transfer it to a new server. If you don&rsquo;t own your domain, all the links to your content that you have accumulated throughout the years will die with your old server. With a custom domain, maintaining hyperlinks in the event of a catastrophic faliure is as simple as editing a couple lines of text.</p>
<p>It is for this reason that I have finally purchased a custom domain for this blog: <a href="https://hayaan.me/">https://hayaan.me/</a>. I hope you will too for your site.</p>
<p>P.S. Domain records are <em>way</em> more complicated and slow than they ought to be.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Centralization of Power</title>
      <link>https://hayaan.me/posts/0021/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Sep 2023 18:47:18 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hayaan.me/posts/0021/</guid>
      <description>Power-hungry execs are destroying the Web.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In the long-ago, email was created to allow easy communication over the Internet. I don&rsquo;t know if you have ever noticed, but email is completely decentralized—a buzzword usually reserved for Web3 startups promising to reform crypto. But in all seriousness, this decentralized nature is why email is so ubiquitous today. Imagine if a hotmail user couldn&rsquo;t email a gmail user: that would be horrible! Because it&rsquo;s open source and decentralized, anyone can create a email server and send email to any other email server. Furthermore, anyone can use any email client to access their email.</p>
<p>This is in stark contrast to the social media platforms of today. Twitter is locked down. Reddit is locked down. Facebook. Instagram. WhatsApp. The list is so long I would probably break the upload limit on my WiFi if I tried to post it all.</p>
<p>In an ideal world, a photo I post on Instagram would show up on Twitter, Reddit, and the like. Any replies on any of the platforms would seamlessly show up on the others. Exactly how email works today between different email apps and services. So why don&rsquo;t all these modern social media platforms talk to each other?</p>
<p>I think its because executives at these companies are trying to centralize their power to make a little extra cash. The centralization of power is something we are witnessing more and more in the corporate world. For example, Twitter and Reddit recently closed down their APIs to third-parties (where they couldn&rsquo;t show advertisements), set vague rules, and forced users who didn&rsquo;t comply out of the platform. Companies don&rsquo;t want to share because that doesn&rsquo;t promote their bottom line.</p>
<p>Centralization of power, like most things, has pros and cons. I&rsquo;m not here to preach about when it is appropriate and when not. However, I can say that consolidating power in a single entity is often to the detriment of massive portions of the user base.</p>
<p>The Internet would be a less hostile, open place if platforms could talk to each other like email services do.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using the Right Tool for the Job</title>
      <link>https://hayaan.me/posts/0020/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Sep 2023 15:27:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hayaan.me/posts/0020/</guid>
      <description>Things are much easier that way.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A year or so ago, I learned the Rust<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup> programming language. Since its first stable release in 2015, it has quickly developed a hold on the world of systems programming. It is well loved because it enforces memory safety, something many existing systems languages, like C, do not.</p>
<p>Rust was designed from the ground up to be a <em>systems</em> programming language, used to build performance-critical software like operating systems and embedded applications. But then people go and try to build websites with it. I admit, I <a href="https://github.com/omega1510/webassembly">am</a> <a href="https://github.com/omega1510/todo">guilty</a> of this, too.</p>
<figure><a href="https://www.smbc-comics.com/comic/qc">
    <img loading="lazy" src="comic.png"
         alt="Part of a comic from SMBC."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Part of a comic from <a href="https://www.smbc-comics.com/comic/qc">SMBC</a>.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>What I have learned, though, is that things are often easier when you use the right tool for the job. As much as I hate javascript, I will still use it if I need to build a website. And as much as I love Rust, I will come running back Python for any data manipulation.</p>
<p>Picking the right tool from the outset saves you from <em>so</em> much frustration. For example, I have sunk countless hours into modifying and customizing my macOS system, something it is clearly not meant to allow. I have also put in large amounts of effort to try and get Windows games running on other operating systems. I could have avoided stress and frustration if I had customized Linux instead and ran Windows to play games.</p>
<p>Making something do a thing it wasn&rsquo;t meant to do is akin to taking an exam with a piece of charcoal instead of a pencil. Sure, it works in theory, but it&rsquo;s so stupid no one would actually do it. But when it comes to software, everyone suddenly calls it innovation, not stupidity.</p>
<section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
<p>This article is <strong>not</strong> endorsed by the <a href="https://foundation.rust-lang.org/policies/logo-policy-and-media-guide/">Rust Foundation</a>™®© :)&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>RSS and Algorithms</title>
      <link>https://hayaan.me/posts/0019/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Sep 2023 16:23:18 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hayaan.me/posts/0019/</guid>
      <description>How to limit algorithms&amp;#39; control on you.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In &ldquo;<a href="https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/why-ai-scary-robots-already-control-you-muhammad-hadi-yusufali">Why is AI Scary? Robots Already Control You,</a>&rdquo; M. Hadi writes:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The robots have been taking over for years now.</p>
<p>Now, when we open our phone, we literally open our mouths to the hundreds upon thousands of algorithms, waiting to be fed by them. We stare at our home screen, waiting for new notifications to pop up before tapping them at superhuman speed. The concerning part is not that we&rsquo;re seeing what other people have messaged us, or catching up on what&rsquo;s happening in the world—it&rsquo;s that most of the time, we&rsquo;re not consciously making the decision to do so. We&rsquo;re just letting these algorthims, these AIs, detect what happens next in our lives.</p>
<p>And we&rsquo;ve gotten used to it. We open ourselves up to YouTube, to TikTok, to Instagram, just going on those sites or apps whenever we want a &ldquo;break&rdquo;—just being fed more and more content. This &ldquo;break&rdquo; is nothing more than us wanting to stop controlling ourselves, wanting to be controlled by others.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is why I love RSS. No multi-national <del>devils</del> corporations, no algorithms, no artificial intelligence—just control. RSS is a technology that lets you view posts from many different websites as a feed. For example, if I really like a blog, I will add it to my RSS aggregator. If I start to dislike a blog, I can just remove it. No algorithms serving me content to control me and maximize my watch time. I have full control.</p>
<p>One thing I find particularly dangerous with algorithms is news websites. They try to serve you headlines that incite an emotional response, not ones that give you an actual overview of the news. This way, they can have a massive influence on what the public believes. It is a modern-day version of the content censorship that was widespread in totalitarian governments, like the Soviet Union. Using RSS is especially important in this case.</p>
<p>I think everyone should use RSS wherever they can to limit the control AI has on them.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Outsourcing Thinking with Artificial Intelligence</title>
      <link>https://hayaan.me/posts/0015/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Sep 2023 18:55:57 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hayaan.me/posts/0015/</guid>
      <description>ChatGPT thinks so we don&amp;#39;t have to.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I have no doubt that artifical intelligence is the next breakthrough technology. I am sure that you have seen the myriad of startups sticking machine learning into places it shouldn&rsquo;t go. Already generative AI has reformed the education space, forcing teachers and schools to adapt or fall behind.</p>
<p>Like every breakthrough technology, research in the field follows a sigmoid curve. It starts out slow, then it feels like everything is using it all of a sudden, then it flattens out as innovation hits a plateau. With AI, it is impossible to tell where we are on that curve. I sincerely hope that we are nearing the end, that this technology has hit its limit and cannot improve any more.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/posts/0015/sigmoid.svg" type="" alt="A sigmoid curve."  /></p>
<p>Why do I feel this way? A scary pattern emerges when we look at the consequences of widespread adoption of previous breakthrough technologies. When the camera came along, we could offload our responsibility to remember the events in our life to the camera. No longer did we have to fill our brains with information about our experiences; we could rely on a photograph instead. The result: our memories of an object <a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/0956797613504438">are limited</a> when we take a photo of that object.</p>
<p>I fear that if we begin outsourcing all our thinking to artifical intelligence, we will lose the ability to think. In my view, the ability to think critically is humanity&rsquo;s greatest strength. If we rely on generative AI to draw connections and link ideas, we <strong>will</strong> forget how to do it ourselves. And that scares me.</p>
<p>I am reminded of H. G. Wells' 1895 novella <em>The Time Machine</em>. In it, the upper class of humanity has slowly made its life easier and easier through manipulation of its environment and of the workers beneath it. With no problems to solve, these future humans have devolved into animals with no ability to think. The workers, who have always relied on themselves to get by, become the new ruling class.</p>
<p>I hope that artificial intelligence has peaked. If it hasn&rsquo;t, it will come to destroy us, slowly boiling us like frogs.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Opting Out of AI Web Scraping</title>
      <link>https://hayaan.me/posts/0011/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Sep 2023 22:02:56 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hayaan.me/posts/0011/</guid>
      <description>Why do I have to &amp;#34;opt-out?&amp;#34;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>If you open my website&rsquo;s <a href="https://omega1510.github.io/robots.txt">robots.txt</a>, you will see that it includes the following lines:</p>
<div class="highlight"><div class="chroma">
<table class="lntable"><tr><td class="lntd">
<pre tabindex="0" class="chroma"><code><span class="lnt">1
</span><span class="lnt">2
</span><span class="lnt">3
</span><span class="lnt">4
</span><span class="lnt">5
</span></code></pre></td>
<td class="lntd">
<pre tabindex="0" class="chroma"><code class="language-yaml" data-lang="yaml"><span class="nt">User-agent</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="l">GPTBot</span><span class="w">
</span><span class="w"></span><span class="nt">Disallow</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="l">/</span><span class="w">
</span><span class="w">
</span><span class="w"></span><span class="nt">User-agent</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="l">ChatGPT-User</span><span class="w">
</span><span class="w"></span><span class="nt">Disallow</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="l">/</span><span class="w">
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table>
</div>
</div><p>What do these lines of code do? Well, they stop OpenAI&rsquo;s ChatGPT from learning from my blog.</p>
<p>OpenAI recently unveiled GPTBot, a piece of software that lets them harvest data from the web to train their artificial intelligence models on. If you take issue with that, like I do, then adding those lines to your website prevent it from scraping the content you wrote.</p>
<p>I, and many other people, don&rsquo;t want artifical intelligence benefiting from my blood, sweat, and tears for free. I find it deplorable that you must &ldquo;opt-out&rdquo; of this process. What about people who have no idea that their data is being harvested and used, or who aren&rsquo;t technically inclined enough to block GPTBot? Will their data be used without compensation until the end of time?</p>
<p>The way it should work is that you must opt-in specifically, and only then will OpenAI scrape your website. Unfortunately, we all know this won&rsquo;t happen. All OpenAI cares about is profit, and that won&rsquo;t happen if they actually respect people&rsquo;s basic right to privacy.</p>
<p>I recently talked about this with a friend. He told me that AI is the future of using the web, and if I block ChatGPT, I&rsquo;m going to lose out on a lot of readers. My opinion may change in the future, but as of now, so be it.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Operating Systems Are Bloated</title>
      <link>https://hayaan.me/posts/0008/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Aug 2023 16:45:03 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hayaan.me/posts/0008/</guid>
      <description>There are so many apps included, and you have to use them.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I have been using Pop_OS!, a popular Linux distribution, on my laptop for years. Recently, I also switched my old desktop over to the lightweight operating system. When people argue over what system is the best, they often only consider macOS or Windows. However, a user of either system will not consider where both fail because they have never experienced what they could have had. Because I use neither, I think I can provide a unique perspective on the shortcomings of both options.</p>
<p>I first had the idea to write about this when I replaced the Gnome desktop environment that came default with Pop_OS! with another piece of software called i3. It was a much better experience, and I wondered why other people do not make similar modifications to their computers. I soon realized, however, that modifications like this are not even possible when you are using a more conventional operating system.</p>
<p>Historically, operating systems did what they said on the can: operate the system. They allowed applications, which were defined by the user, to communicate with the computer&rsquo;s hardware, and vice-versa.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/posts/0008/operating-system.svg" type="" alt="The historical role of operating systems."  /></p>
<p>But now, operating systems have gone from being a simple interface between applications and hardware to all-powerful processes demanding the user&rsquo;s complete submission. Gone are the days of choosing what your computer runs; operating systems provide default apps, and you <strong>must</strong> use them.</p>
<p>Many points of contention in the &ldquo;what OS is best&rdquo; debate arise from the operating system making decisions for you and not letting you change its choice. For example, people argue over the placement of buttons on either the top-left or top-right corner. macOS has gone with the former option, while Windows chooses the latter. But this decision should never have been the OS&rsquo;s to make! This decision has always been made by the user when they installed a desktop environment; who let Apple or Microsoft choose?</p>
<p>To illustrate again: Microsoft recently rounded the corners of windows in a visual revamp of their operating system. Historically, this has been an option in applications called compositors, which the user could choose to install. If they weren&rsquo;t satisfied with one, they could choose another. By rounding corners of windows with no way to undo it, Microsoft made a decision that the user had the right to make.</p>
<p>I suppose that Apple and Microsoft are doing this in the name of &ldquo;crafting an experience.&rdquo; I have nothing against that. In fact, I applaud them for taking the time to create great applications, like desktop environments, window managers, and compositors, and including them with their operating systems. I take issue with the fact that they have stolen the user&rsquo;s ability to switch to another application they find better.</p>
<p>Both tech giants already include apps that fit this philosophy. Apple provides Disk Utility on their computers, a great app to format and manage storage drives on your computer. They also don&rsquo;t force you to use it, letting you install other drive-managing software. If they took this stance with other parts of their operating systems, it would be better for everyone. Regular users would get their default apps and experience, while advanced ones could install they apps they want installed.</p>
<p>In the meantime, I&rsquo;ll stick with Linux, where I can choose exactly what code my CPU is crunching through.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Artificial Intelligence and Copyright</title>
      <link>https://hayaan.me/posts/0004/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Aug 2023 22:07:58 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hayaan.me/posts/0004/</guid>
      <description>Court rules that AI-generated images can&amp;#39;t be copyrighted.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Last week, a U.S. District Judge <a href="https://www.reuters.com/legal/ai-generated-art-cannot-receive-copyrights-us-court-says-2023-08-21/">ruled</a> that images created solely by artifical intelligence without any human input cannot be copyrighted under U.S. copyright law. He stated that human authorship is a prerequisite for copyright, and simply owning the AI responsible for generating a work is not enough to give you authorship of its creation. I am very interested in seeing how this precedent plays out in court cases in the coming years.</p>
<p>In particular, the issue of how much editing a human needs to do to the generated content for it to be considered a derivative work is of paramount importance and interest. If you have ChatGPT write an article, but you make a website and post it online, is that enough &ldquo;modification&rdquo; for you to be given ownership over the work?<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup> What if you perform minimal edits, like removing the [YOUR NAME] bits the AI sometimes outputs? Is that &ldquo;modification?&rdquo; SAG-AFTRA, the Hollywood writers union that is currently on strike over the use of AI in the industry, has a vested interest in not allowing copyrighting of works where even a little bit of generative AI was used.</p>
<p>AI is meant to be used like an assistant. So if you and your assistant work on something together, and your assistant releases it to the public domain, how much editing to you need to do for you to claw back ownership and copyright it?</p>
<p>I am going to be closely following developments in the realm of artificial intelligence and copyright; I find this field, filled with moral landmines and massive grey areas, to be fascinating.</p>
<section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
<p>By the way, absolutely no generative AI is used when writing for this blog. In fact, I barely use generative AI at all because I find its use to be morally questionable and intellectually debillitating. Sorry OpenAI, I prefer to think for myself.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
