<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Hayaan&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>https://omega1510.github.io/blog/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Hayaan&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 24 Aug 2023 16:30:15 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://omega1510.github.io/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Do Evil People Exist?</title>
      <link>https://omega1510.github.io/blog/posts/0005/do-evil-people-exist/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Aug 2023 16:30:15 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://omega1510.github.io/blog/posts/0005/do-evil-people-exist/</guid>
      <description>What does &amp;#34;evil&amp;#34; even mean?</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This question was first asked to me nearly a decade ago by an elementary school teacher. It has stuck with me all these years because, as far as I can tell, it was my first introduction to the world of philosophy. When the teacher asked it to that group of young third-graders, no one could answer him. Now, I think I might have a response.</p>
<h2 id="what-is-an-evil-action">What is an Evil Action?</h2>
<blockquote>
<p>An evil intention perverts the best actions, and makes them sins.<br>
— Joseph Addison</p>
</blockquote>
<p>To clear up any ambiguity, we need to determine what exactly makes an action evil. We may define it very broadly, such that an evil action is one where there is even a small amount of immorality present, regardless of the greater good. This would include the classical &ldquo;bad&rdquo; actions, like murder and lying, as well as immoral acts performed for a large benefit, as in the case of the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trolley_problem">trolley problem</a>. Nearly every action we perform could be considered evil under this definition. An action performed solely for our benefit could be considered selfish, and therefore evil, for example.</p>
<p>Instead, one may limit the broad definition of evil, stating that an evil action is any action where the bad in it outweighs the good. This definition necessarily encompasses all immoral acts while omitting ones performed for the greater good.</p>
<p>A second alternative is a strict definition, where an action must be completely morally wrong, without any shred of good, for it to be considered evil. With this view, we omit many actions that are technically wrong but that nobody would call &ldquo;evil,&rdquo; such as white lies, for even a white lie would be beneficial to someone. However, we also exclude nearly every immoral act because most of them contain at least a little good; they are, so to speak, for the lesser good, but still good nonetheless.</p>
<p>I find the second definition—the limited yet broad one—to be the most appealing. It leaves wiggle room for actions performed for the greater good but includes things we would normally consider evil, like homicide.</p>
<h2 id="what-is-an-evil-person">What is an Evil Person?</h2>
<blockquote>
<p>To prefer evil to good is not in human nature; and when a man is compelled to choose one of two evils, no one will choose the greater when he might have the less.<br>
— Plato</p>
</blockquote>
<p>An evil person could be someone who simply performs bad actions, no matter how little. If we accept this definition, in combination with either broad definition of evil, to be evil is to be human because men are not angels: we always incline towards a little bit of sin as consequence of our free will.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup></p>
<p>If we consider an evil person as someone who performs only evil and no good, we get nowhere. Even Hitler, who we can all agree is evil, still paid his officers' wages. He did not wake up every morning with <em>just</em> the intention to kill. If we take this approach, no one in the history of mankind has been evil.</p>
<p>In my opinion, the best definition of an evil person, as with the case of evil actions, is someone who performs more evil than they do good. With this definition and the medium definition of evil, all the classical &ldquo;evil&rdquo; figures—Stalin, Hitler, Mao—would all be considered evil.</p>
<p>The answer to the question &ldquo;Do evil people exist?&rdquo; depends on your definition of &ldquo;evil&rdquo; and &ldquo;evil person.&rdquo; It can be argued that everybody is evil, or nobody is evil, or that only a few bad figures are evil. It is a matter of nuance and personal preference, and there is no right answer.</p>
<section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
<p>Even if you don&rsquo;t believe in free will, I think you can agree that no one acts morally all of the time, regardless of whether they are responsible for their actions.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Artificial Intelligence and Copyright</title>
      <link>https://omega1510.github.io/blog/posts/0004/ai-and-copyright/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Aug 2023 22:07:58 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://omega1510.github.io/blog/posts/0004/ai-and-copyright/</guid>
      <description>Court rules that AI-generated images can&amp;#39;t be copyrighted.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Last week, a U.S. District Judge <a href="https://www.reuters.com/legal/ai-generated-art-cannot-receive-copyrights-us-court-says-2023-08-21/">ruled</a> that images created solely by artifical intelligence without any human input cannot be copyrighted under U.S. copyright law. He stated that human authorship is a prerequisite for copyright, and simply owning the AI responsible for generating a work is not enough to give you authorship of its creation. I am very interested in seeing how this precedent plays out in court cases in the coming years.</p>
<p>In particular, the issue of how much editing a human needs to do to the generated content for it to be considered a derivative work is of paramount importance and interest. If you have ChatGPT write an article, but you make a website and post it online, is that enough &ldquo;modification&rdquo; for you to be given ownership over the work?<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup> What if you perform minimal edits, like removing the [YOUR NAME] bits the AI sometimes outputs? Is that &ldquo;modification?&rdquo; SAG-AFTRA, the Hollywood writers union that is currently on strike over the use of AI in the industry, has a vested interest in not allowing copyrighting of works where even a little bit of generative AI was used.</p>
<p>AI is meant to be used like an assistant. So if you and your assistant work on something together, and your assistant releases it to the public domain, how much editing to you need to do for you to claw back ownership and copyright it?</p>
<p>I am going to be closely following developments in the realm of artificial intelligence and copyright; I find this field, filled with moral landmines and massive grey areas, to be fascinating.</p>
<section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
<p>By the way, absolutely no generative AI is used when writing for this blog. In fact, I barely use generative AI at all because I find its use to be morally questionable and intellectually debillitating. Sorry OpenAI, I prefer to think for myself.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My Thoughts on The Double</title>
      <link>https://omega1510.github.io/blog/posts/0003/the-double/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Aug 2023 21:00:51 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://omega1510.github.io/blog/posts/0003/the-double/</guid>
      <description>It was a blood-curdling, psychological exploration of identity with an underwhelming plot.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>Sorrow is concealed in gilded palaces, and there’s no escaping it.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Last night I finished reading <em>The Double: A Petersburg Poem</em>. It is the third of Dostoevsky&rsquo;s works that I have read. I am usually a huge fan of the author; my favorite book is <em>Crime and Punishment</em> and I also loved <em>Notes from the Underground</em>. I love the deep explorations of morality and psychology that are woven throughout his books. His dialogue is unlike anything else that I have read: it is so real, personal, and engaging.</p>
<p><em>The Double</em> was an impulse buy from the bookstore on Stanford&rsquo;s campus. I was looking for a copy of <em>The Idiot</em> or <em>The Brothers Karamazov</em>, but <em>The Double</em> caught my eye instead. The description on the back piqued my interest even further. I bought the book, thinking that I was in for an enjoyable and thought-provoking read.</p>
<p>Boy, was I wrong. <em>The Double</em> was nothing like <em>Crime</em> or <em>Notes</em>. In my opinion, this is one of Dostoevsky&rsquo;s weaker works and was not very enjoyable to read. I found the plot drawn out and repetitive, and the prose difficult to read. I would normally attribute the latter gripe to the translator, but I have read elswhere that the original Russian text of the book was just as complicated.</p>
<p>The dialogue and psychological exploration was still outstanding, marking the novel as distinctly Dostoevskian. Similar to his other novels, it features an blood-curdling ability to force you into the protagonist&rsquo;s head. I felt like I was inside his thoughts, following him hand-in-hand in his psychological descent.</p>
<p>However, this forte was held back by a plot I could not fully understand. It closely followed the protagonist&rsquo;s actions, but when your protagonist is an anxious schizophrenic, the story becomes incredibly confusing.</p>
<p>In the end, I agree with Dostoevsky&rsquo;s own opinion of the work. He stated in <em><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A_Writer%27s_Diary">A Writer&rsquo;s Diary</a></em>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Most decidedly, I did not succeed with that novel; however, its idea was rather lucid, and I have never expressed in my writings anything more serious. Still, as far as form was concerned, I failed utterly.</p>
</blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why is Reading Gendered?</title>
      <link>https://omega1510.github.io/blog/posts/0002/why-is-reading-gendered/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Aug 2023 19:11:52 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://omega1510.github.io/blog/posts/0002/why-is-reading-gendered/</guid>
      <description>Where did all the fiction-loving men go?</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I read a lot. Now that I think about it, I probably read too much. I stay up for hours most nights engrossed in the expansive world behind my Kindle&rsquo;s screen, dying to learn about the latest adventure the protagonist has gotten caught up in.</p>
<p>When introducing myself to someone new, I usually say that I read books as a hobby. Recently, a girl I was talking to asked me my favorite book. &ldquo;<em>Crime and Punishment</em>,&rdquo; I responded. She replied, &ldquo;Dostoevsky, right?&rdquo; I can&rsquo;t convey on paper how much joy I felt in that moment.</p>
<p>I realized that my life was missing someone I could really talk to about what I&rsquo;m reading. Unfortunately, I&rsquo;m the only male I know who loves fiction in this way. Some of my friends will gladly read the latest self-help book or thousand-page physics tome, but none of them can get lost in the pages of a good novel.</p>
<p>I wish I had a friend group with whom I could discuss the literature I find myself consumed by. Some people to talk to about the things on my mind. I believe that many men are in a similar situation to myself.</p>
<p>So my question is, when did reading fiction become a woman&rsquo;s thing to do? The statistics are clear: Goodreads <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/blog/show/475-sex-and-reading-a-look-at-who-s-reading-whom">reported</a> in 2014 that women read two times more books published that year than their male counterparts.</p>
<p>What is the cause? According to <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/S0304-422X(00)00003-6">a study</a> published in 2000, girls are more likely to be encouraged by their parents to read at a young age and usually have more free-time to do so later in life.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s a shame that a hobby like reading, widely considered to provide social, intellectual, and personal benefits, must be a gendered activity. To all the parents out there, encourage your sons to read!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hello, world!</title>
      <link>https://omega1510.github.io/blog/posts/0001/hello-world/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Aug 2023 18:44:27 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://omega1510.github.io/blog/posts/0001/hello-world/</guid>
      <description>Why I write.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2 id="motivation">Motivation</h2>
<p>I think it&rsquo;s fitting for the first post on this blog to be an explanation of why I&rsquo;m writing.</p>
<p>One of my friends recently began posting more of his thoughts on social media because he felt that writing had taken a backseat in his life. He wanted to rekindle that quickly fading love for the pen. I don&rsquo;t think that&rsquo;s the case with me.</p>
<p>Neither do I want to attract followers or make money. If I wanted to do that, I would be posting AI-generated content somewhere with more eyes, like Medium.</p>
<p>I discovered a quote that I think sums up my thoughts nicely. Amit G. <a href="https://amitg.blog/my-daughter-was-writing-in-her-journal-today-and-casually-asked-me-why-she-does">writes</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>My daughter went on to scribble happily in her journal. Once she was done, she said, “I love how I feel when I capture everything on my mind in these pages.”</p>
<p>Even I want that now.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I want to write because there is something trapped inside of me angry that I won&rsquo;t let it out. There are way to many thoughts in my head, fighting to be put down on paper. I want this blog to be a place where I can let the little <a href="https://allpoetry.com/poem/8509539-Bluebird-by-Charles-Bukowski">bluebird</a> in my soul roam free, at least for a little while.</p>
<h2 id="future-plans">Future Plans</h2>
<p>This blog will have absolutely no AI-generated content. It will have no advertisements, tracking, or harvesting of data. It will be raw and free: a place where I can write down my thoughts for the world to see.</p>
<p>I recently came across <a href="https://juliacameronlive.com/basic-tools/morning-pages/">Julia Cameron&rsquo;s Morning Pages</a>, where you write three pages from the heart stream-of-conciousness style every morning. That&rsquo;s a little too hardcore for me.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m aiming for posting about 300 words every day on this blog. Some days I&rsquo;ll write more, some days less. It&rsquo;s all about building a habit. Let&rsquo;s see how it goes.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
