<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>reading on Hayaan&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>https://hayaan.me/tags/reading/</link>
    <description>Recent content in reading on Hayaan&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 19 Sep 2023 14:13:08 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://hayaan.me/tags/reading/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>On Reading Philosophy</title>
      <link>https://hayaan.me/posts/0029/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Sep 2023 14:13:08 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hayaan.me/posts/0029/</guid>
      <description>Everyone should do it.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Of all the classes that I have taken so far, Philosophy has had the largest impact on me. I took it earlier this year at <a href="https://foothill.edu">Foothill College</a> on a whim, and I am glad that I did.</p>
<p>First, there are the more straightforward benefits of the class. It was very writing-heavy, with a 900 word essay and two shorter 200 word responses due every week. The midterm exam was a 5 page paper, and the final was two 2 ½ page papers. My writing, especially about complex topics, increased as a result of the course.</p>
<p>Second, there are the philosophical benefits. I feel as if a whole field of knowledge has been opened to me. Before, epistemology, ontology, or ethics never even crossed my mind. Now, I can think about these topics critically and form my own opinions.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, philosophical texts are incredibly dense and hard to read. They are definitely not your everyday novels. I admit, I have only ever finished a handful of philosophical books, choosing instead to read excerpts and essays. In this limited fashion, I have read Plato, Aristotle, Descartes, Kant, Sartre, and so on.</p>
<p>In my opinion, excerpts are an easy way to get into philosophy. They take what can sometimes be a 1000+ page tome, and give you a taste of a main argument for an idea. The textbook I used in my course was Cottingham&rsquo;s <a href="https://www.wiley.com/en-us/Western+Philosophy%3A+An+Anthology%2C+2nd+Edition-p-9781405124775"><em>Western Philosophy: An Anthology</em></a>, which, as it says in the title, is an anthology of western philosophical texts. For someone getting into philosophy, this is an easy way to get your foot in the door.</p>
<p>I highly recommend everyone read philosophy and not be discouraged by the difficult nature of writings in the field. No one is expecting you to takle Kant as your first read; instead, you can get a quick overview of major philosophical texts by reading an anthology of excerpts.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Finding Balance on The Road</title>
      <link>https://hayaan.me/posts/0028/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Sep 2023 16:54:16 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hayaan.me/posts/0028/</guid>
      <description>We are all carrying the fire.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>What&rsquo;s the bravest thing you ever did? He spat in the road a bloody phlegm. Getting up this morning, he said.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Yesterday I finished <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Road"><em>The Road</em></a> by Cormac McCarthy. I usually don&rsquo;t read contemporary literature, but I stumbled on this book in a Reddit thread about emotional books, and decided to give it a shot. It was published in 2006, and I feel that it was a breath of fresh air given that I mostly read 19th-century Russian novels.</p>
<p>The book describes the journey of a father and son in a post-apocalyptic landscape decimated by an unspecified cataclysm. There are many themes in the book, but I would like to focus on reason vs. emotion in this post.</p>
<p>The father is far from optimistic. Numerous times throughout the plot, the son asks his father if there are other good people still alive somewhere, like Mars. The father makes no delay in shutting this optimism down, saying that it&rsquo;s impossible for humans to survive on other planets.</p>
<p>Instead, he is focused on survival in a completely rational way. He doesn&rsquo;t let emotion cloud his judgement. The boy falters in fear when entering an abandoned house, but the father goes in knowing they must find food or die.</p>
<p>However, the end reveals that it is a mix of rationality and emotion that helps you achieve salvation. The boy&rsquo;s life is saved after the father&rsquo;s death only because he emotionally trusted a random stranger. Similarly, the father and son have only survived this long because the father put logic first.</p>
<p>This shows that it is important to strike a balance in our life. Going full on Rousseau is not the right decision, nor is going full on Enlightenment. It is in the middle that we can best live our lives.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Look at the Gulag with Ivan Denisovich</title>
      <link>https://hayaan.me/posts/0018/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Sep 2023 15:46:15 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hayaan.me/posts/0018/</guid>
      <description>Time to yell at Stalin.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>During his years in prisons and in camps he’d lost the habit of planning for the next day, for a year ahead, for supporting his family. The authorities did his thinking for him about everything—it was somehow easier that way.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I just finished reading <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/One_Day_in_the_Life_of_Ivan_Denisovich"><em>One Day in the Life of Ivan Denisovich</em></a>, so it&rsquo;s time for me to have a good yell at the Soviet Union.</p>
<p>But first, some background about the book. It&rsquo;s author, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aleksandr_Solzhenitsyn">Aleksandr Solzhenitsyn</a>, was imprisoned in the Soviet Union&rsquo;s harsh Gulag work camp system under Stalin from 1945 to 1953. After his release, Solzhenitsyn began writing <em>One Day</em>, a narrative of life in the Gulag. The book helped spark a wave of anti-Soviet sentiment after its publication.</p>
<p>I am almost struggling to give a consice overview of the Gulag&rsquo;s psychological horror outlined in this novel. It is so dense and multifaceted that no short post like this can do it justice. Whenever you think that Solzhenitsyn has covered all the atrocities of the labor camps, the book hits you with another way the Gulag tries to break its prisoners. Does the horror stop at physical work? No, there are no fixed wages and another person screwing up means no one gets any money. Does it stop there? No, corruption in the Gulag&rsquo;s administration means you can&rsquo;t file complaints either. Does it stop there? Absolutely not.</p>
<p>I am so upset that people were abused to the point that they must lick other people&rsquo;s bowls of soup clean to get enough nutrition. And camps like this aren&rsquo;t a relic of the past; they still exist in places like China and Burma.</p>
<p>The novel is still very much applicable to us in the current era. It continues to show us the depths of the human soul through the eyes of prisoners in the Gulag.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lessons from The Old Man and the Sea</title>
      <link>https://hayaan.me/posts/0013/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Sep 2023 20:39:55 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hayaan.me/posts/0013/</guid>
      <description>Simple writing conveying deep meaning.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>&ldquo;But man is not made for defeat,&rdquo; he said. &ldquo;A man can be destroyed but not defeated.&rdquo;</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Thus states the old man in Ernest Hemingway&rsquo;s timeless novel, <em>The Old Man and the Sea.</em> I recently finished this book, which was one of the best novels I have read in the past few months. In it, Hemingway uses incredibly simple language to craft a beautiful plot of willpower and determination. The book features an old fisherman who goes out to sea further than he has ever gone, and ends up catching a fish weighing over a thousand pounds.</p>
<p>Through the book&rsquo;s protagonist, Hemingway symbolizes the peak of manhood: an unwavering—and sometimes detrimental—resolve to achieve a goal. Hemingway shows that it is not raw power or an aggressive personality that makes a man; rather, it is determination in the face of certain defeat that really matters. In other words, manliness is the ability to always rise from defeat.</p>
<p>I planned to list out some of the specific lessons and symbolism in <em>The Old Man and the Sea</em>. However, this article does it much better than I can: <a href="https://www.artofmanliness.com/character/manly-lessons/lessons-in-manliness-from-the-old-man-and-the-sea/">Lessons in Manliness from The Old Man and the Sea</a>. I highly recommend everyone read it after they have read Hemingway&rsquo;s original novel.</p>
<p>I think that it is to every man&rsquo;s advantage to read <em>The Old Man and the Sea</em>. It&rsquo;s a short novel, too; it comes in around 100 pages, and its simple language means anyone can easily benefit.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My Thoughts on The Double</title>
      <link>https://hayaan.me/posts/0003/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Aug 2023 21:00:51 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hayaan.me/posts/0003/</guid>
      <description>It was a blood-curdling, psychological exploration of identity with an underwhelming plot.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>Sorrow is concealed in gilded palaces, and there’s no escaping it.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Last night I finished reading <em>The Double: A Petersburg Poem</em>. It is the third of Dostoevsky&rsquo;s works that I have read. I am usually a huge fan of the author; my favorite book is <em>Crime and Punishment</em> and I also loved <em>Notes from the Underground</em>. I love the deep explorations of morality and psychology that are woven throughout his books. His dialogue is unlike anything else that I have read: it is so real, personal, and engaging.</p>
<p><em>The Double</em> was an impulse buy from the bookstore on Stanford&rsquo;s campus. I was looking for a copy of <em>The Idiot</em> or <em>The Brothers Karamazov</em>, but <em>The Double</em> caught my eye instead. The description on the back piqued my interest even further. I bought the book, thinking that I was in for an enjoyable and thought-provoking read.</p>
<p>Boy, was I wrong. <em>The Double</em> was nothing like <em>Crime</em> or <em>Notes</em>. In my opinion, this is one of Dostoevsky&rsquo;s weaker works and was not very enjoyable to read. I found the plot drawn out and repetitive, and the prose difficult to read. I would normally attribute the latter gripe to the translator, but I have read elswhere that the original Russian text of the book was just as complicated.</p>
<p>The dialogue and psychological exploration was still outstanding, marking the novel as distinctly Dostoevskian. Similar to his other novels, it features an blood-curdling ability to force you into the protagonist&rsquo;s head. I felt like I was inside his thoughts, following him hand-in-hand in his psychological descent.</p>
<p>However, this forte was held back by a plot I could not fully understand. It closely followed the protagonist&rsquo;s actions, but when your protagonist is an anxious schizophrenic, the story becomes incredibly confusing.</p>
<p>In the end, I agree with Dostoevsky&rsquo;s own opinion of the work. He stated in <em><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A_Writer%27s_Diary">A Writer&rsquo;s Diary</a></em>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Most decidedly, I did not succeed with that novel; however, its idea was rather lucid, and I have never expressed in my writings anything more serious. Still, as far as form was concerned, I failed utterly.</p>
</blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why is Reading Gendered?</title>
      <link>https://hayaan.me/posts/0002/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Aug 2023 19:11:52 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hayaan.me/posts/0002/</guid>
      <description>Where did all the fiction-loving men go?</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I read a lot. Now that I think about it, I probably read too much. I stay up for hours most nights engrossed in the expansive world behind my Kindle&rsquo;s screen, dying to learn about the latest adventure the protagonist has gotten caught up in.</p>
<p>When introducing myself to someone new, I usually say that I read books as a hobby. Recently, a girl I was talking to asked me my favorite book. &ldquo;<em>Crime and Punishment</em>,&rdquo; I responded. She replied, &ldquo;Dostoevsky, right?&rdquo; I can&rsquo;t convey on paper how much joy I felt in that moment.</p>
<p>I realized that my life was missing someone I could really talk to about what I&rsquo;m reading. Unfortunately, I&rsquo;m the only male I know who loves fiction in this way. Some of my friends will gladly read the latest self-help book or thousand-page physics tome, but none of them can get lost in the pages of a good novel.</p>
<p>I wish I had a friend group with whom I could discuss the literature I find myself consumed by. Some people to talk to about the things on my mind. I believe that many men are in a similar situation to myself.</p>
<p>So my question is, when did reading fiction become a woman&rsquo;s thing to do? The statistics are clear: Goodreads <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/blog/show/475-sex-and-reading-a-look-at-who-s-reading-whom">reported</a> in 2014 that women read two times more books published that year than their male counterparts.</p>
<p>What is the cause? According to <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/S0304-422X(00)00003-6">a study</a> published in 2000, girls are more likely to be encouraged by their parents to read at a young age and usually have more free-time to do so later in life.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s a shame that a hobby like reading, widely considered to provide social, intellectual, and personal benefits, must be a gendered activity. To all the parents out there, encourage your sons to read!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
