<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>philosophy on Hayaan&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>https://omega1510.github.io/blog/tags/philosophy/</link>
    <description>Recent content in philosophy on Hayaan&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 08 Sep 2023 17:53:13 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://omega1510.github.io/blog/tags/philosophy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Evil and an Omnipotent God</title>
      <link>https://omega1510.github.io/blog/posts/0017/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Sep 2023 17:53:13 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://omega1510.github.io/blog/posts/0017/</guid>
      <description>How can evil exist when God is good?</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This post is an addendum to <a href="../0016">yesterday&rsquo;s post</a> about Thomas Aquinas&rsquo;s five ways to argue for the existence of God. In the same book where his arguments were published, the <a href="https://www.newadvent.org/summa/1002.htm#article3">Summa Theologica</a>, the Catholic philosopher addressed a possible objection to the omnipotence of God.</p>
<p>He begins by describing the objection:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>It seems that God does not exist; because if one of two contraries be infinite, the other would be altogether destroyed. But the word &ldquo;God&rdquo; means that He is infinite goodness. If, therefore, God existed, there would be no evil discoverable; but there is evil in the world. Therefore God does not exist.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>What does Aquinas mean by this? He first states a premise that two infinite things—good and evil in the passage—cannot both exist together. If either one is infinite, then it must overpower the other. For example, a world with an infinite source of good cannot contain any evil. Furthermore, if God exists, then He must be infinitely good, and His goodness must overpower all evil in the universe. However, there is clearly evil present in the world we live in. Therefore God, or at least an omnipotent one, cannot exist our universe.</p>
<p>On the surface, this objection seems convincing. It strikes an emotional chord with most people, who have been through calamities in their lives and often questioned the supremacy of God thereafter. The objection is a variation of the classic question: &ldquo;why do bad things happen to good people?&rdquo;</p>
<p>Aquinas addresses this remonstration by citing Augustine of Hippo, a bishop who defended Christianity against philosophical attacks in his writings. Augustine argues that God&rsquo;s power is so great that He would not allow evil to exist unless he could bring good out of evil; therefore, even a universe with evil in it can contain an infinitely good God because all evil actions have the potential for good.</p>
<p>As Aquinas puts it:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>This is part of the infinite goodness [and mercy] of God, that He should allow evil to exist, and out of it produce good.</p>
</blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Aquinas&#39; Quinque Viae</title>
      <link>https://omega1510.github.io/blog/posts/0016/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Sep 2023 17:24:59 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://omega1510.github.io/blog/posts/0016/</guid>
      <description>A Catholic philosopher&amp;#39;s proofs for the existence of God.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The existence of God has been a point of contention among philosophers for as long as philosophy has existed. Even Socrates called into question the supremacy of the ancient Greek gods in his home of Athens nearly half a millenium prior to the birth of Christ. Still today, theists are engaged in vigorous debate with modern philosophers over rational evidence for God&rsquo;s existence.</p>
<p>In the mid-13th century, Catholic philosopher Thomas Aquinas composed his magnum opus, the <a href="https://www.gutenberg.org/cache/epub/17611/pg17611.html"><em>Summa Theologica</em></a>, a religious textbook for students beginning their studies in theology. He recognized the necessity of proving God&rsquo;s existence in his work, and wrote the <a href="https://www.newadvent.org/summa/1002.htm#article3">Quinque Viae</a>: five ways to argue that God does indeed exist.</p>
<p>Aquinas' arguments are admittedly weak when exposed to modern scrutiny, but they provide a basis for many modern arguments favoring God. They are heavily cited, &ldquo;classic&rdquo; theological arguments, not necessarily fool-proof ones. Nevertheless, they create an excellent baseline on which to form a complete understanding of God&rsquo;s existence.</p>
<h2 id="the-argument-of-the-unmoved-mover">The Argument of the Unmoved Mover</h2>
<p>In the world we live in, everything is in motion. But for something to be in motion, it must have been moved by something else. For example, if I push a block of wood, a chemical imbalance in my muscles acted a force on the block. The chemical imbalance also itself was caused by electrical impulses in my nerves, which in turn were caused by something else.</p>
<p>This chain cannot be infinitely long; it therefore follows that there must have been a first mover in the beginning who, while unmoved, exerted a force on the universe. This primeval entity is understood to be God.</p>
<h2 id="the-argument-of-the-first-cause">The Argument of the First Cause</h2>
<p>We live in a world of cause and effect. Things are caused by other things. It is not possible for a thing to cause itself, so it must have been caused by another distinct event. This second event is itself the effect of another cause, and so on. For example, a plant grows because of sunlight, which exists because of the sun, which exists because of gravity.</p>
<p>Like in the first argument, this chain cannot continue ad infinitum. A first cause must exist that began the chain but was not caused itself. This cause is God.</p>
<h2 id="the-argument-from-contingency">The Argument from Contingency</h2>
<p>Things can be broadly divided into two groups: the possible and the necessary. Possible things are those that have the ability to not exist. For example, cats are possible entities because they live and die, and if you go back far enough in time, no cats existed.</p>
<p>For every possible thing, there is a time in the past when it did not exist. If everything is possible, then there must exist a time long in the past when nothing existed at all. If this is the case, then nothing could exist now, because nothing can come into existence except through a being that already exists.</p>
<p>Therefore, it follows that a necessary being—something that <em>must</em> exist and cannot be nonexistent—existed in the beginning. Everything that exists draws its existence back to it. This necessary being is God.</p>
<h2 id="the-argument-from-degree">The Argument from Degree</h2>
<p>All things vary in their imitation of the True, the Good, and the Beautiful. Some entities imitate at a higher degree, and are subsequently considered better. For example, in a room of people, there is always a tallest.</p>
<p>Something must exist that is the most True, Good, and Beautiful—the &ldquo;tallest&rdquo; of all existence, so to speak. Furthermore, the most perfect in any group is the cause of all qualities of that group, like how fire, the pinnacle of heat, is the cause of all hot things. There must be a being to which all truth, nobility, and beauty is devoted—a being perfect in every way. This being we call God.</p>
<h2 id="the-argument-from-final-cause">The Argument from Final Cause</h2>
<p>Inanimate objects in the world behave in regular and predictable ways. If their design was based purely on chance, then their behavior would not be predictable. For these inanimate objects, which lack intelligence, the fact that they move toward the same purpose means they must have been directed by something else with intelligence and influence.</p>
<p>Therefore, a being must exist that is the source of all common purpose in the governance of the world. God is this being.</p>
<h2 id="discussion">Discussion</h2>
<p>I find myself agreeing with much of what Aquinas has to say. His simple language and illustrative examples helped me refine the thoughts floating around my head. I am sure we have all heard the Argument of the Unmoved Mover and Argument from Final Cause before, but to read it from the source is an enlightening experience.</p>
<p>Modern philosophy has not failed to uncover fallacies in Aquinas' arguments; in addition, his writings leave a distinctly Platonic/Aristotelian aftertaste in my mouth. But there is something endearing about Aquinas' attempt at distilling things I have heard for years into concrete philosophical statements. There is undoubtedly a reason why Aquinas is so commonly referenced in philosophy courses: he took a concept as perfect as God and made it comprehensible by the imperfect human cognition.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Condemned to Be Free</title>
      <link>https://omega1510.github.io/blog/posts/0006/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Aug 2023 18:34:58 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://omega1510.github.io/blog/posts/0006/</guid>
      <description>Do humans have free will?</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>This essay was submitted in partial fulfillment of an Intro to Philosophy course at <a href="https://www.foothill.edu/">Foothill College</a>.</em></p>
<p>For centuries, philosophers have debated what free will is and whether we even possess it. In an increasingly scientific world, some of them argue that our choices are determined only by the laws of physics. In contrast, others believe that free will is an essential component of human nature. Although the universe appears to operate in a deterministic way, the idea of free will is instrumental in our moral accountability and individual identity.</p>
<p>One thing that separates us as humans from animals is that we take responsibility for our actions. An animal acts purely based on its desires; a lion cannot be held accountable for killing a gazelle. On the other hand, humans can be punished for their unjust acts. This innate responsibility and accountability follows from the belief that humans have free will, that we choose to transgress. We must be responsible for our actions if there were alternate actions we could have taken. In a debate with English philosopher Thomas Hobbes, Dr. John Bramhall argued exactly this. He stated: “No man blames fire for burning whole cities; no man taxes poison for destroying men; but [he only blames] those persons who apply them to such wicked ends. If the will of man be not in his own disposition, he is no more a free agent than the fire or the poison.” Our world is built on the punishment of immoral actions. In many cases, a man only acts good because he is required to do so. If there was no free will, he could not be held accountable for his actions and all punishments would be baseless.</p>
<p>In addition to moral accountability, the idea of free will is also essential in our sense of personal identity. In his book <em>Being and Nothingness</em>, French philosopher Jean-Paul Sartre suggests that our choices define who we are, and that without the ability to make choices, we would be nothing more than objects in the world. Sartre believes that humans have the ability to transcend their circumstances, “project forward”, and make choices that create their own identities. He argues that when we make a moral decision, we are not just choosing between different options—we are also choosing what kind of person we want to be. For example, when we choose to tell the truth instead of lying, we are not just choosing the &ldquo;right&rdquo; action—we are also choosing to be a truthful person. Free will is necessary for this development of identity. A purely deterministic system would take this away.</p>
<p>Breakthroughs in science suggest that the universe is deterministic. Everything exists in the movement of invisible atoms. Our consciousness is just neurons firing inside our skulls. How can one be free to will in this situation? While it is true that the universe appears to operate in a deterministic way, this does not necessarily mean that free will is an illusion. St. Augustine of Hippo targets this idea in his book <em>The City of God</em>. In his writing, he takes the determinist universe to be like God, who “knows unchangeably all things which shall be.” Augustine argues that, even though there is a God who knows everything, we still have the ability to make and act on our choices. This is because our wills work in conjunction with the will of God to predetermine things. God&rsquo;s foreknowledge of future events is based on his infinite wisdom and understanding of human nature, rather than on any causal relationship between God&rsquo;s knowledge and human actions. Therefore, even if the universe operates deterministically, it is still possible that humans have free will because our wills are part of the determining process.</p>
<p>The debate about free will has been ongoing for centuries, with some philosophers arguing that our choices are determined by the laws of physics and others arguing that free will is an essential component of human nature. While breakthroughs in science suggest that the universe is deterministic, the idea of free will remains instrumental in our moral accountability and personal identity. Without free will, we would not be able to take responsibility for our actions, nor would we be able to define ourselves as individuals. Even the deterministic universe suggested by science remains compatible with free will. When considering all these factors, it becomes clear that humans, as Sartre puts it, are “condemned to be free.”</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Do Evil People Exist?</title>
      <link>https://omega1510.github.io/blog/posts/0005/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Aug 2023 16:30:15 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://omega1510.github.io/blog/posts/0005/</guid>
      <description>What does &amp;#34;evil&amp;#34; even mean?</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This question was first asked to me nearly a decade ago by an elementary school teacher. It has stuck with me all these years because, as far as I can tell, it was my first introduction to the world of philosophy. When the teacher asked it to that group of young third-graders, no one could answer him. Now, I think I might have a response.</p>
<h2 id="what-is-an-evil-action">What is an Evil Action?</h2>
<blockquote>
<p>An evil intention perverts the best actions, and makes them sins.<br>
— Joseph Addison</p>
</blockquote>
<p>To clear up any ambiguity, we need to determine what exactly makes an action evil. We may define it very broadly, such that an evil action is one where there is even a small amount of immorality present, regardless of the greater good. This would include the classical &ldquo;bad&rdquo; actions, like murder and lying, as well as immoral acts performed for a large benefit, as in the case of the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trolley_problem">trolley problem</a>. Nearly every action we perform could be considered evil under this definition. An action performed solely for our benefit could be considered selfish, and therefore evil, for example.</p>
<p>Instead, one may limit the broad definition of evil, stating that an evil action is any action where the bad in it outweighs the good. This definition necessarily encompasses all immoral acts while omitting ones performed for the greater good.</p>
<p>A second alternative is a strict definition, where an action must be completely morally wrong, without any shred of good, for it to be considered evil. With this view, we omit many actions that are technically wrong but that nobody would call &ldquo;evil,&rdquo; such as white lies, for even a white lie would be beneficial to someone. However, we also exclude nearly every immoral act because most of them contain at least a little good; they are, so to speak, for the lesser good, but still good nonetheless.</p>
<p>I find the second definition—the limited yet broad one—to be the most appealing. It leaves wiggle room for actions performed for the greater good but includes things we would normally consider evil, like homicide.</p>
<h2 id="what-is-an-evil-person">What is an Evil Person?</h2>
<blockquote>
<p>To prefer evil to good is not in human nature; and when a man is compelled to choose one of two evils, no one will choose the greater when he might have the less.<br>
— Plato</p>
</blockquote>
<p>An evil person could be someone who simply performs bad actions, no matter how little. If we accept this definition, in combination with either broad definition of evil, to be evil is to be human because men are not angels: we always incline towards a little bit of sin as consequence of our free will.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup></p>
<p>If we consider an evil person as someone who performs only evil and no good, we get nowhere. Even Hitler, who we can all agree is evil, still paid his officers' wages. He did not wake up every morning with <em>just</em> the intention to kill. If we take this approach, no one in the history of mankind has been evil.</p>
<p>In my opinion, the best definition of an evil person, as with the case of evil actions, is someone who performs more evil than they do good. With this definition and the medium definition of evil, all the classical &ldquo;evil&rdquo; figures—Stalin, Hitler, Mao—would all be considered evil.</p>
<p>The answer to the question &ldquo;Do evil people exist?&rdquo; depends on your definition of &ldquo;evil&rdquo; and &ldquo;evil person.&rdquo; It can be argued that everybody is evil, or nobody is evil, or that only a few bad figures are evil. It is a matter of nuance and personal preference, and there is no right answer.</p>
<section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
<p>Even if you don&rsquo;t believe in free will, I think you can agree that no one acts morally all of the time, regardless of whether they are responsible for their actions.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
